What is artificial intelligence?
Hi! I've been looking
into this artificial intelligence thing.
It's fascinating.
I investigated and spoke
with experts and researchers.
I read articles, attended conferences,
delved deeper, and dug.
I went all the way to the Pharaoh's tomb.
Basically, I went as far as I could.
Watch out! This is serious stuff.
By the way, we thought of you
because we gave you all the sources.
That way, you can check for yourself
and, above all,
explore the subjects that interest you.
All good? Here we go.
History of Algorithms.
Algorithms are all around us.
Content recommendations
on Facebook are algorithms.
GPS location that tells me
about traffic jams is an algorithm.
-Facial recognition...
-Algorithm.
Good. Yes, but what are algorithms?
Let's start from the beginning, computing.
Computing is about processing information
automatically.
It relies on machines
capable of processing data
-thanks to...
-Algorithms.
Good, Theo, that's good.
You're with me, that's nice.
Now, algorithms,
stop me if I'm wrong, are a bit like...
a cooking recipe.
It is a series of instructions
to be followed in a certain order
to perform a task automatically.
Automatically means without the need
to understand or think.
This is perfect for a machine.
Once you have this list of instructions,
you translate it into a language
that a computer can understand,
and you get a computer program.
Computers run any program that describes
an algorithm perfectly and very quickly,
and that's very impressive.
Moreover, in the 1950s,
researchers began to dream.
They imagined algorithms
that would make computers
as intelligent as humans.
As Nicolas Rougier,
an Inria researcher, explains,
there were some great advances
up until the end of the 1970s,
but then we were discouraged.
The promised results were not forthcoming.
Research funds stopped flowing,
and there was the first AI winter.
Ten years later,
there was a surge in expert systems
that tried to reproduce the reasoning
of a specialist such as a doctor.
Still, the human knowledge
had to be put into the machines,
whereas what we wanted was
for the machines to learn by themselves.
A second AI winter happened.
At the end of the 1990s,
a breakthrough came.
Deep Blue, IBM's supercomputer,
beat the world chess champion,
Garry Kasparov.
In 2016, another breakthrough,
a Google algorithm
beat one of the best Go players
in the world,
despite not having been thought possible
for several years.
In fact,
the history of artificial intelligence
alternates between high-profile advances
and major disappointments.
Now we're back in the boom phase.
Have our computers
become intelligent or not?
We should clearly understand and define
what biological intelligence is
to define artificial intelligence.
Before, being an excellent chess player
was a sign of intelligence.
Today, that is no longer enough
because the machine does it automatically.
Biological intelligence is defined
in the same way
as artificial intelligence,
which is a fascinating question.
I will try to explain to you today
what biological intelligence is in 2020.
Biological intelligence.
At the same time
as artificial intelligence,
the cognitive sciences were born,
which study human intelligence.
They have made it possible
to identify the various mechanisms
at work in the way thought functions.
This thought allows us
to perceive, speak, move,
memorise, reason, plan,
be abstract at times
or creative for the best of us.
These are our cognitive functions.
To stimulate human intelligence,
the idea was
to reproduce cognitive functions.
To achieve this,
the researchers favoured two approaches
which are somewhat similar
to how we learn,
either through the transmission
of knowledge or through trial and error
based on observation
of the world and experimentation.
The two complement each other.
The symbolic approach tries to imitate
how humans reason logically
and use their knowledge.
As Thalita Firmo Drumond,
an Inria doctoral student, explains,
a certain amount of knowledge
is transmitted to us through experiences,
rules and procedures.
This is how school learning,
such as learning how to add, is done.
When I add something,
I can explain how I do it step by step.
It is then possible to write a program
explaining to the machine
how to proceed step by step.
The machine will then be able
to perform it much faster than I can
and without any mistakes.
This approach has given rise
to expert systems
that try to reproduce the reasoning
of a specialist,
such as a doctor or lawyer,
to solve a problem.
This approach was very popular
in the 1980s.
Other knowledge comes from experience,
where it is much more difficult to explain
how it is achieved, such as
riding a bike or recognising a cat.
I can explain to you how to ride a bike,
but you'll only know
how to ride if you pedal.
You have to experience it.
The other approach,
the digital or connectionist approach,
tries to imitate
how humans learn by trial and error
from their experiences.
This approach is the one
that is in the spotlight today.
You know, machine learning
and the famous neural networks.
OK, but you still haven't answered
the real question.
What is intelligence?
Biological intelligence?
I'm getting there.
Frédéric Alexandre,
a computational neuroscience researcher,
gives us the following answer.
"Intelligence means being able
to respond quickly
to a complex situation.
Intelligence means finding
the right answer
rather than the best one.
Intelligence means finding out
what is important in the information.
Intelligence means knowing
how to adapt if conditions change
or how to react
to an unexpected situation."
All of this is done by using
a strategy typical of living beings
that combines emotion,
motivation and creativity.
What is strong and specific
about biological intelligence,
which artificial intelligence
does not have,
is the complementarity
of these emotional and logical aspects.
Yes. Common sense.
If you like.
Avoiding the illusions
of general intelligence,
which is far from the case,
it would be better to speak
of artificial intelligence in the plural.
All the artificial intelligences
we encounter in real life
are just very technical and specific.
They can only do the task
they have been programmed
or configured for.
A program
that beats the world chess champion
cannot recognise a duck.
However, when it comes to a specific task,
they are highly efficient
and often better than us.
From the lab to our homes.
In recent years, artificial intelligence
has once again entered a phase
of exponential development.
This is thanks to the increase
in available data,
the processing power of computers,
and the optimisation
of algorithms, of course.
Voice or image recognition
or translation programs,
which were scoffed at a few years ago,
now work in a way that can be astonishing
thanks to machine learning.
Artificial intelligence has emerged
from laboratories
and is now permeating
and impacting all areas of society,
from finance to agriculture,
from medicine to education,
and even into our homes.
In today's digital world,
we unknowingly encounter
and use artificial intelligence
in our everyday objects,
cameras,
recommendation systems on social networks,
and connected speakers.
A world of algorithms.
Humans must decide
what the systems can do for us,
not the other way around.
As these technologies
profoundly shape our society,
understanding how they work is crucial.