Hold on! I know who to call. You'll see.
The hotline.
Guillaume. Hello. Long time no speak.
What brings you here today?
-Artificial intelligence.
-That's great.
The more I hear about it,
the less I understand it.
I used to think it was great.
I'm with my cousin Theo who just showed me
an article about Stephen Hawking,
-you know, the greatest researcher ever,
-Yes.
-who says, "The development
of full artificial intelligence
could spell the end of the human race."
Yeah, it's pretty scary what the guy says.
Who is afraid of AI?
Yes, but Guillaume,
you have to ask yourself who is talking?
-I told you, it's my cousin Theo.
-Hi.
No, I mean Stephen Hawking.
He was a top scientist in cosmology,
but AI is not his field.
Instead, listen to a real expert
on the subject,
such as Jean-Gabriel Ganascia,
who is a computer science researcher
and head of the ethics committee
at the CNRS.
The term is still misunderstood.
Many people say, "Does it exist?
Do you believe
in artificial intelligence?"
because they imagine
that it's a kind of fantasy,
the idea that a machine
will suddenly be brought to life
by intelligence.
I will show you that this is not the case.
Artificial intelligence
is a scientific discipline.
That's what's important.
Yes, of course, there are fantasies
about artificial characters
with intelligence.
Pinocchio, Frankenstein.
Terminator, they're going to kill us all.
No, let me stop you right there.
A robot is not necessarily an AI,
it's a mechanical carcass with sensors
and a computer in it,
and only sometimes,
there are algorithms
called artificial intelligence inside.
In contrast, Theo,
look at your smartphone.
It doesn't look like a robot.
There's no AI in there.
-Yes, there is.
-Exactly.
Getting back to the Terminator.
In the real world,
there is no intelligence capable
of doing everything like we see in films,
and there's no saying it will ever happen.
After that, everyone is free
to believe what they want,
but these are only beliefs, not science.
But Elon Musk and other figures,
including Internet bosses,
are also very concerned,
even though they are the ones
-developing these technologies.
-That's true.
Yes, it smells like a scam.
We must not become paranoid.
Of course,
these technologies raise important ethical
and societal questions,
which must be addressed
as scientific advances are made.
"Science without conscience
is but the ruin of the soul",
said Rabelais in the 15th century.
Bravo, Guillaume.
Yes, all the current concerns
are perfectly legitimate
because AI has a real impact on society.
Everyone must understand
what it is really about
so that we can discuss the economic
and societal choices that must be made.
You see, Theo, your father is right.
You don't need to be a mechanic
to drive a car,
but it's still better
to look under the bonnet
to see how it works
and especially how it brakes.
We'll look into it. OK?
OK.
What is artificial intelligence?