The hotline.
Guillaume. What's on your mind today?
My cousin Theo told me about a pizza
powered by artificial intelligence.
There's no way.
No, he is right.
The food industry is also in on it.
I wonder what it would taste like.
Have you ever licked a circuit board?
How do they get
artificial intelligence into a pizza?
I'm missing something here.
AI on everything?
They don't really put AI in the pizza.
They put lots of data
in a machine learning model.
For example, data about ingredients,
customer preferences, recipe trials
and tester feedback.
Using all this data,
the model will generate
many different recipes,
without preconceived ideas
about their taste,
and predict
whether they will appeal to customers.
Wait a minute. If I understand correctly,
you are telling me
that our society now uses
-statistics to create pizzas?
-Yes.
Machine learning algorithms can be used
in many areas,
and marketing is no exception
as long as data can be fed
into the models.
Does it need a lot of data?
Yes, you need lots of data.
Besides, the more data you give them,
the more machine learning models learn
how to predict the next data correctly.
Do you see what I mean?
I can better see how big data connects,
but it still doesn't add up.
I need to dig deeper.