Machine learning and data.
When we talk
about artificial intelligence today,
we most often hear "machine learning".
There are two ways to learn.
The one that comes from the knowledge
that is passed on to us
is the symbolic approach,
and the one that comes from experience
that we acquire is the digital approach.
Machine learning is based on
the digital approach, i.e., experience.
The principle is not telling
the computer exactly what to do.
No, we'll program it
to learn from examples
based on statistical approaches.
Learning to learn.
I'll use the example of David Louapre,
researcher and science populariser,
to explain.
Let's say you are a botanist.
You are walking in the forest.
You make some observations.
You measure the height
and diameter of the trees
and record it all in a data table.
Once you get home,
you draw a graph
with the diameter on the x-axis
and the height on the y-axis,
and place your data on it.
You quickly you realise that the two
are linked and that by drawing,
in this case,
a straight line through the points,
this will allow you to
predict the height of a tree
from its diameter.
Machine learning works the same way.
You provide the calculation
with input data,
and output data.
You train it to find the relationship
between the two, the straight line,
by adjusting the parameters
of the calculation.
This is what we call generalisation.
Once this learning phase is done,
we can make predictions.
That means producing a correct answer
for similar data,
that the program wasn't trained on.
That's what machine learning is all about.
To be able to make predictions.
Predictions
that are not necessarily predictable.
How do these machines learn?
In fact,
there are several learning techniques.
We'll just talk about the two main ones.
Supervised learning is the example
of the botanist that we just saw.
First, there is a training phase
where data labelled
by humans feed the algorithm.
That's why it's called "supervised".
CAT
Then, there's a prediction phase
where the algorithm
will give an answer
for data that it has never seen.
98% CAT
This is used to extrapolate value,
but it's also used to differentiate
cats from dogs, for example.
2% CAT
Then, there is reinforcement learning
where the algorithm learns
by being immersed in an environment,
and where it will adjust its parameters
depending on the positive
or negative reaction
that follows each of its actions.
A bit like a child learning to ride a bike
who falls and gets up again,
This algorithm is mainly used for robots
or autonomous agents
and also works very well
in virtual worlds
or in specific situations.
Perfect for the game of Go,
but not so good for autonomous driving.
Imagine if a car had to crash
thousands of times
before a machine learns to drive it.
Every app has its own algorithm.
I've heard of deep learning.
What is it exactly?
Neural networks.
Deep learning is a machine learning method
which is based
on artificial neural networks.
Artificial neural networks
offer a calculation method
which is inspired by the brain.
Biological neurons are cells
connected to each other.
Simply put,
when a neuron receives a signal,
it can either send nothing,
or send its own signal.
Artificial neurons
are mathematical constructs
that roughly mimic how real neurons work.
Each neuron combines its inputs
and provides an output.
To make complicated functions,
you can combine many neurons.
That's what we call
an artificial neural network.
This method is not new.
In fact, it dates back to the 1950s,
but it requires
considerable computing power and data.
In the mid-2000s,
with the increase in processor capacity
and the mass of data
made available by the Internet,
everything changed
and we could move to the deep phase.
The neurons are arranged
in successive layers.
The results of the first layer of neurons
will be used as an input
to the calculations of the others,
and so on.
The more layers there are,
the deeper the network.
That's why learning
by deep neural networks
is called deep learning.
Let's take an example
on image recognition.
How is the neural network
able to learn on its own
how to recognise a picture of a cat,
when all it sees are pixels?
From the thousands of cat photos
that it was exposed to,
labelled as a cat,
it will be able to adjust the parameters
of its calculation
to extract characteristics
that determine what a cat is.
Once the programme has acquired
the notion of what a cat is,
it can make a prediction on a new image.
Sure, at the beginning,
the network will get a lot wrong,
lots of mistakes,
but the model will be built by adjustment,
by little successive changes.
By comparing these results
and adjusting its calculation,
it can identify a cat in a picture
that it's never seen before.
Exactly! It's about statistics.
As Marc Schoenauer explains,
research director at Inria,
"It's not about programming one thing
to get an exact result,
but rather to find patterns,
even if inaccurate, from data."
Hence, the importance of data.
You can have the best algorithm
in the world.
But if the data is bad,
or poorly classified,
the results will be too.
The data challenge.
For example, if we train an algorithm
to recognise a sheep in a picture
by showing it white sheep,
it won't be able to recognise black sheep.
The data must be varied
and sufficiently numerous.
Without this,
generalisation is not possible.
You also need well classified data.
To properly train AI
to recognise sheep in a picture,
not only do you need many sheep pictures,
but they also have to be well annotated.
In other words, in this case,
the sheep is framed
and that it is specified that the frame
corresponds to a sheep.
As we have seen,
this involves thousands of images
which must be annotated by hand
so that the AI can learn correctly
and then make good predictions afterwards
from images which are no longer annotated.
A long and arduous task,
but also very important
because bad annotations
lead to bad predictions.
Sometimes we annotate data
without even realising it.
You know, like some CAPTCHAs
where you have to find the boxes
that have cars in them.
You are annotating an image or checking
that it has been properly annotated,
and not necessarily proving
that you are a human being.
What's more,
there is a great deal of invisible work
done by humans
who are paid a few euros per day
to click on hundreds of images.
Have you heard about
Amazon's Mechanical Turk?
Yes, I went to the site.
-Indeed, the rates are ridiculous.
-The click workers.
Where does the data come from?
Data can be collected automatically
via sensors such as telescopes,
surveillance cameras, microphones
and sensors measuring air quality.
They can also be produced by users,
in particular via the queries
submitted to a search engine,
publications, comments on social networks,
connected objects and purchases
made on a credit card.
It is an exchange of free services
between the big groups and us.
That's it.
When it's free, you are the product.
Yes, it's true.
The big American or Chinese private groups
have large amounts of data on tap,
which raises problems related to independence.
Today in China,
a social node system has been set up
to evaluate citizens' behaviour.
Data is mainly collected
via surveillance cameras,
social networks,
and an AI assigns a score that allows
or not to access public service.
This mass of data is boosting
start-ups at the same time
because whoever has the data
has the power to run the models
and improve them.
Hence the importance of the GDPR
to regulate all these practices,
so that the European states
and their citizens
have a little more control
over their personal data.
Big data consumes a lot, doesn't it?
Data is stored in data centres.
The cloud is not an actual cloud.
It's pizza boxes,
entire server towers
that heat up and need to be cooled
with air conditioning.
Algorithms, when they are at AI level
need exceptional computing capacity,
which means supercomputers
which bring together several dozen
of thousands of processors
in huge buildings.
Yes, it consumes a lot
and it's a risk for the whole system.
It is up to us to be vigilant
about the cost-effectiveness
of artificial intelligence.
It can be a great tool
which provide a lot of services,
but also there are also apps
that push us to consume or track us.
Like any technology,
it depends on how it is used.
It's up to us to make sense of it!