The hotline.
Guillaume, what brings you here today?
My cousin Theo told me
that artificial intelligence
could replace us at work.
Maybe for him,
but I don't see how
AI could replace me in the office.
Unless it has a lot of good jokes.
Are humans worth scrapping?
I've been looking into this
and some studies
suggest that it will affect one
in two jobs in the next 10 to 20 years.
Yes, other studies talk about 15%.
It's a tricky topic.
The same question arose
during the industrial revolution,
when machines replaced 90%
of jobs in agriculture.
Still, nobody today would want
to go back to scythes or, for that matter,
part with their washing machine.
This is the story of innovation.
Yes, of course, but this is different.
Today, when we talk about computers,
we mean automatic information processing.
It's not about replacing workers.
It's about replacing intellectual work.
The advent of artificial intelligence
means that all our abilities
and ourselves will eventually be replaced.
Holiday for everyone!
Most jobs are not disappearing,
but being reinvented.
As Gregory Verdugo,
an economist and researcher, said,
"It's hard to predict
what will be technically automatable."
You're missing the point here.
No, I'm not.
I'm just saying that I'm not a medium.
I don't know
if my job will ever be fully automated.
But I do know
that I don't want to live in a society
that lets artificial intelligence
make a decision for me.
What do you want? What do you think?
Before I answer you,
I want to know a little more.
OK.
I'll conduct my own investigation
to make up my own mind.