Is Artificial intelligence working for us?
AI is all around us,
and asks societal, democratic, ethical
and political questions.
Who and what does it work for?
Who controls whom?
What role will we let it play?
In short, what kind of society
do we want to live in?
The exciting part
of research on artificial intelligence
is that it allows us to make advances
on our understanding
of human intelligence.
At the same time,
the debates about this technology
push us to reflect on what makes us human,
our place as citizens and our societies.
It's a huge topic
that merits your attention.
Shall we think about it together?
Emotions and creativity.
Firstly, I would like to question
the human-machine relationship.
To simulate human intelligence,
AI attempts to replicate
human cognitive functions.
Reasoning, motor skills,
language and vision,
but that's not all.
Being creative is also part
of these cognitive functions.
As I'm speaking,
AIs are creating music,
books, film scripts,
-paintings...
-and even pizza.
The results can be amazing.
Well, I can't say just yet
in the case of pizza,
as I haven't tasted it.
Does this mean that AI is creative?
I have to say that we are still far
from Hergé or the Beatles!
Current AIs that we design
are not capable of inventing.
On the other hand, they can imitate.
According to Albertine Meunier,
a digital artist
who uses the web as material,
AI is only a tool,
but it offers an infinite number
of possibilities, new shapes
and options we wouldn't have thought of.
And can machines have emotions?
Machines can behave like us in appearance.
Significant progress has been made
to detect human emotion
and react accordingly
with the appropriate emotion.
But, as Laurence Devillers said,
research director at LIMSI/CNRS,
Machines don't feel anything.
They simulate.
But you can make people believe
that they feel something
using sensors, for example.
If you touch the sensor,
a signal is detected,
and the machine reacts
But in fact, we don't even really need
to have a robot around the program.
Voice alone is enough to captivate us.
Just look at the effect
of the voice speakers.
In 300 metres, turn right.
We must not neglect our inclination
towards anthropomorphism,
which is very powerful.
If I ask myself all these questions,
it seems necessary to me to question
the relationship
we're going to have with these machines,
and above all, where they will fit in.
Decision-making aids?
Artificial intelligence algorithms
don't just reproduce
mechanical tasks for us.
They can be great decision-support tools
in a lot of sectors
like transport, banking, insurance
and protection.
One of the most interesting areas
is medicine.
For example,
algorithms can help diagnose tumours
by analysing X-rays.
In the future,
algorithms could diagnose appendicitis
or predict the appearance of a tumour
before it is visible on the image.
This is incredible!
It's great.
Of course,
as long as everything goes to plan.
Algorithms can be flawed.
It's nothing serious when deciding
on toothbrush recommendations,
but what if these decisions
have an impact on my personal life,
in the medical or judicial field?
You can't just respond,
"I had nothing to do with it, officer.
It was the machine's decision".
No!
It's essential to provide explanations
and justifications for the recommendations
that have been made,
or the decisions taken, right?
That's the whole point
of what we call "explainability".
The technique that is trending today,
deep neural network learning,
or deep learning,
works a bit like a black box.
We can't really explain
how the neural network gets its results,
at least in a way
that is intelligible to a human being.
So there is research
to make these systems more transparent,
and in addition,
we are making huge progress in this area.
Alexei Grinbaum,
a philosopher of science CERNA
and CEA physicist,
explains that we need to design a system
in such a way
that it will always be possible
to trace the causal chains
that led to any action
or decision made by the machine.
For example,
putting another learning system
to explain what the first system does,
provides the first look
at what is going on inside.
The black box effect
masks the origin of bias.
These biases come
from the data used to train the program,
but it isn't easy
to analyse it afterwards.
The programme needs vast amounts
of data to learn.
As they say,
it understands quickly,
but it needs a long explanation.
Not enough data,
or not varied enough,
or badly annotated
can lead to poor results.
For example, if we train an algorithm
to recognise a sheep in a picture...
Baaah!
...and it is only shown black sheep,
it will not be able
to recognise any white sheep.
And then they call the AI racist!
In fact, the data is biased
by our own stereotypes.
A machine trained with biased data
reproduces these biases
without even understanding them.
Baaah!
A study published
in the journal Science in 2017
has shown that many biases exist
in human language.
The word man is more often associated
with terms for leadership positions
in the science or engineering sectors.
In contrast, the word woman
is associated with assistant positions
in the arts and humanities sector.
Also, African-American names
lead to bad words.
So, if you don't pay attention
when it comes to AI choosing a candidate
for an engineer position,
the CV of a black woman
will go to the bottom of the pile.
Serge Abiteboul, a researcher
at the Computer Science Department
of the École Normale Supérieure,
tells us about an amazing experiment
done in Israel.
They realised that the probability
of being released by going before a judge
was greater after lunch than before.
It makes me wonder
about my own decision criteria.
Well,
luckily, they have other decision factors
than how full their stomachs are.
In any case, we can say that AI
always reproduces the same behaviour
from the data provided.
Once again we see data's importance
and the motivations
of those who design these machines.
A democratic issue.
It's the eternal question
of the tool and what to do with it.
Of course, it's the humans
who define the software's objectives.
We can discuss this with them,
in fact, it's a must.
And there are not only philanthropists!
Even when you have the best intentions
in the world,
the question remains,
who should decide?
Serge Abiteboul said
that it's not up to the IT people
to decide how to develop an algorithm
that calculates students' fate,
just like it shouldn't be Google
that decides to ban extremist
or fake news sites.
The digital world has developed so fast
that it is still in the western stage,
injustice is everywhere,
the state does not understand enough
to legislate properly
and the citizens are lost.
Many researchers agree that
machines can help us evolve our decisions
by offering us ideas and solutions,
but it's up to humans
to decide which rules
the machines should follow
and, in case of doubt,
to make the final decision.
So what should we do
while we wait for the sheriff?
We are addressing the conscience
of the people who create the algorithms.
We create ethical rules.
The citizens are given keys
so that they can mobilise if necessary.
This is what we are doing!
Yes Theo, exactly,
one building block at a time.
Anyway, I hope this humble work,
made entirely by humans,
will help you to see it more clearly.
It's up to all of us
to embrace artificial intelligence
and invent new uses
to make our lives easier,
more interesting
or simply more beautiful.