There is a whole digital ecosystem
that is being developed around
the teacher and the pupil.
The use of digital technology is widespread
through the most diverse types of devices:
tablets, computers,
and, of course, wifi access.
This digital environment provides access
to information, learning environments,
workspaces, textbooks,
transcripts, school reports,
and many other information and tools.
In addition to all this,
there is also online educational content:
textbooks or possibly free content
such as open educational resources.
Of course, all these materials and resources
do not replace the richness
of the interactions between teacher
and learner and between learners.
Several things happen
on the other side of a platform,
of a screen, but we only see the result.
Teachers are used to picking up
a certain number of clues
in a physical classroom
but they are not all available
in the same way
when they go through digital tools.
The clues that teachers are led to perceive
in a real situation in a classroom
are notably those of engagement
and motivation.
For example,
you can see if a pupil is asleep.
When the noise level rises
you can tell that something is happening.
When all heads are down
during an explanation
of a concept on the blackboard,
you can say
that something unusual is happening.
Even though there are many,
many possible explanations,
being able to pick up on these clues
or the lack of them is important.
When the pupils are no longer
in front of the teacher,
how can you see that they are dropping out,
that they are no longer able to follow,
either because it is too complicated
or the learning format is not adapted to them,
or simply because they do not understand
why they have to follow this course.
It is particularly in these areas,
such as engagement or motivation,
that the exploitation of digital traces
by AI technologies can help the teacher,
as well as the pupil.
More generally,
according to Gartner’s model,
AI technologies,
from the most basic to the most advanced,
can help the teacher to describe
(what happened?),
diagnose (why did it happen?),
predict (what will happen?)
or prescribe
(how to act according to the possible evolution?)
a learning situation to better adapt it
to a pupil or a group of pupils.