During the interaction with digital tools,
the learners leave behind
many “digital traces”.
There are traces they leave without effort,
for example, by accessing a service,
or a server,
they leave a trace of their connection
to that service.
There are also the traces left voluntarily
that demands some effort, by writing,
leaving comments, or rating, for example.
There are also the traces
associated with performance
and the results in activities
present in the digital learning environment.
These whole sets of traces generate data
that can be analysed
by artificial intelligence technologies.
The question we can then ask ourselves is:
How is it possible to analyse
this dataset of digital traces
to help pupils during their learning
and teachers in their pedagogy?
If we look at sports training, we can model
information about the activity duration,
the sleep hours, or recovery hours.
Other traces are much more precise
and can capture the so-called
biological signals,
including the athlete’s emotions.
In this context of sport,
the traces make it possible, for example,
to finetune the athlete’s training routine
or to provide better shoes.
What if we dare to imagine similar tools
that rely on artificial intelligence
to analyse digital traces
but in the educational context?
We can provide the pupils
with very powerful tools that will help them
to make a self-assessment about
their current status in comparison
to their objective competences and behavior,
in relation to the mistakes
they may have made,
but also in relation to the achieved successes.
It is also possible to provide them
with other useful information,
using predictive models.
We can, for instance,
offer them additional personalized resources
that will help them to enhance
their chances to succeed
on their learning path.
From the teachers’ perspective, we can ask:
How can the available learning traces
be used to help teachers to adapt
their teaching strategies and pedagogy?
By using a tool such as a dashboard,
the analysis and visualization
of students’ behavior can allow teachers
to better understand the status of a pupil
or a group of pupils at a given moment
or over time and, eventually,
to offer recommendations of actions
and resources to support teachers’ decision.
These recommendations
can be associated with explanations
to enable teachers to decide
whether or not to exploit them.
Finally, can all these insights
provided by AI tools
also enable the institution
to organise itself better, to renew itself,
and to no longer have these corridors
so well defined,
but paths that are more undulating,
a little more complex, and even,
above all, much more personalised?