Imagine this metaphor
that depicts a narrow point of view
for school as a place that offers courses
that can be represented
as well-defined “courses corridors”.
These courses corridors have an entry point,
which is the one through
which we enter the formal education system,
and they also have a more or less
distant objective,
which is the one that allows our arrival,
in the long term, to the professional world.
These corridors are relatively
well mapped out, clear, and well defined,
and they are designed for pupils
who are ready to follow them.
Pupils are well aligned,
well seated in the starting blocks,
and ready to start working
and learning efficiently.
We are all aware, and particularly
the actors in the formal education systems,
that for some pupils,
each corridor is an obstacle course race
with sometimes significant difficulties.
Some pupils will drop out.
Others, fortunately, will succeed.
But the reality
is much more complex than that.
When we look at the starting line,
we see pupils who are
indeed well prepared, and ready to go.
There are others who,
although they are ready to go,
are not well equipped or trained:
they do not have the right tools,
they do not have the right concepts.
They don’t have the right preparation
or the right environment
that will allow them to succeed.
Others are there, ready to participate,
but don’t fully understand
what is expected of them,
and are then faced with difficulties.
And then there are those who,
from the start, either quickly give up,
or are not really ready to start.
Of course, each pupil will build
his or her own learning path
with the help of the teachers,
and all paths are good.
Whether they go through the sand dunes
or stay in the well-marked corridors,
whether they take other paths
or whether they take a few breaks
to regain their strength and recover.
Depending on each individual preferences,
these paths can be followed alone
or supported by other pupils,
teachers or supervisors.
So, where, and how
can artificial intelligence be used
to ensure that each pupil
will follow the learning path
that is best suited to their needs
and this path will allow them to succeed?
Why can’t we do as the motion tracking
applications do?
That means, providing better analysis,
through artificial intelligence,
of digital learning behaviors
and moving towards greater
personalization of learning paths.