Creating this course
in the European context
of artificial intelligence in education
actually came about
as a peer-to-peer learning activity
between different colleagues
from ministries in Slovenia as of 2019.
I had the opportunity to present
the Artificial Intelligence
innovation partnership
to learn French and maths for pupils
aged six to eight
that the French Ministry just launched.
It generated considerable interest
among all the participants.
In 2019, AI was emerging in all sectors
of activity and education too,
and there were many questions
about what to do.
Therefore, together with Italy, Ireland,
Luxembourg and Slovenia,
we decided to submit this project
under the Erasmus programme framework
to tackle these issues together
and not manage them country by country
since we have different education systems.
The objective of this training
in the European context
is to be able to approach things
at three levels.
Demystify and understand
what AI can bring to education.
Experimenting and using resources
that include AI
in an intelligent way, funnily enough.
Finally,
to develop the necessary digital skills
for all educators and students today,
or at least to understand
the use of AI is part of it,
to integrate the ethical aspect
into the projects from the start.
In other words, what is AI for?
What are the challenges
and expected results of AI?
How do we implement
and use these AI resources?
Finally, how can we also integrate
issues that may bring ethical reflection
beyond regulatory matters from the outset?
That's why we chose
to try to approach this AI in education
starting from
an age group of 15, 16 years old
with pupils at the beginning
of high school for maths
and science on the one hand,
and for the learning
of modern languages on the other hand,
because we needed two fields
of experimentation,
two areas of experimentation
could be done for the project's duration.
The first level, "Demystifying
and understanding AI", aims both,
I would say, to reassure those
who are afraid,
and to calm down those
who are enthusiastic,
so that finally
we can identify which AI techniques
can provide solutions to the problems
I am trying to solve,
and also to identify possible biases
from the start.
It's all the issues that allow you to say,
"We need to be able to test AI algorithms
and AI techniques
associated with resources
within a framework of trust,
so that we can finally make a real attempt
to measure what to do afterwards."
It's not magical, nor is it frightening.
There is no need
to be afraid of these techniques.
You need to understand
the general principles.
You don't need to be an expert,
but understand the general principles
to make good use of these AI techniques
in assisting the teacher
with their teaching workload
or assisting the student
if they are learning independently,
for example, with specific software.
The second level of experimenting
and testing AI-enabled resources
is to get past your fears
or general enthusiasm,
to be able to identify their needs
or define their goals clearly,
and to test in a trusting environment.
In particular, by carefully looking
at what was in line with the regulations,
and the rules,
so that we can finally test for real.
We'd test the resources
in a framework of trust
and check with our colleagues,
ourselves or with the pupils
what is relevant or not relevant.
In fact, it's a question of discovering
and measuring, if possible,
also with research teams,
but everything depends.
We just need to act with a level head,
having taken
all the necessary precautions,
from the point of view, I'd say,
of all that can be bias at the start,
and at the end,
and to be always in charge,
so to speak,
of what we do and how we trust.
It also makes it possible for the teachers
to gain trust
and through feedback finally,
to demystify what AI techniques are
and to use them well,
to identify well which AI techniques,
what are their objectives
and finally to be able to measure
if it is relevant or not
in my class context,
in the general context,
of what there is to do
in relation to the curricula
when I am with the students
I have in front of me.
The third level, in fact,
invites the teacher
not to remain focused
only on AI techniques
or on disciplinary learning
and the AI techniques they use,
but to be part of a more global discussion
with their colleagues,
educational team, and their school team,
to be able to participate fully
in the student's academic pathway
and by integrating ethical issues
on the one hand,
but also by thinking
that this is part of digital literacy,
of the wider digital skills
that every educator,
student and, more generally,
every individual must have
in the current context
of the digital transition.