The objective of this training
in the European context
is to finally approach things
at three levels.
Demystify and understand
what AI can bring to education.
To experiment and use resources
that include AI
in an intelligent way, funnily enough.
And lastly,
to develop the necessary digital skills
among all educators and students today,
and AI is part of that.
At any rate, a good understanding
of how AI is used is part of it,
in order to integrate
the ethical dimension
into the projects from the start.
In other words, what is AI for?
What is the challenge
and the expected result of AI?
How can we implement
and use these AI resources?
Finally,
how can we also integrate questions
that can introduce ethical reflection
beyond the regulatory issues
from the start?
This is why
we chose to try to approach this AI
in education from an age group
of 15-16 years old
with students at the beginning
of high school
for mathematics and science
on the one hand,
and learning foreign languages
on the other hand,
because we needed two experimental fields,
two experimental domains,
which would be feasible
over the duration of the project.