To face the challenges
in the European context,
with the help of a guide to use
AI and data in education ethically,
which the European Commission produced,
there are different levels.
Of course, the first challenge
in a European context
is to be able to address
different education systems.
It is to be able to address
different training systems,
even though
we all have the same questions.
So, in this European context,
we need to face this challenge and do it
through identical questions
and solutions which can be the same
while considering
a whole range of variations
between countries, regions
and in my local system.
From the local
to the national and the European,
the first challenge we must face
is to identify
the problems to be solved
and the solutions to be proposed together,
while still leaving room for adaptation
to each Member State.
Of course, depending on
the Member States' priorities,
we must provide added value
on a European scale
as per each one's competences.
The second challenge is to have
an ethical and reasoned approach
that invites us to experiment and identify
the use cases in which this AI
and these data to be mobilised are relevant
to achieve an objective
that we have set ourselves,
whether it's a learning objective
or a learning path objective.
In the end, to identify this, it is about using AI
to adapt the solutions we can provide
to the needs of each student,
to work on the rhythms,
to work on the paths
they may take throughout their schooling,
but also to provide in other cases,
such as that of pupils
with special needs,
adapted solutions
which effectively allow us
to serve the learner
and the teacher.
This is really very important.
This challenge must also be combined
with feedback on what we are doing
and an important link with research
in education and digital education,
which is also one of the challenges,
in other words, to be accompanied
as much as possible
and not to remain alone.
We must never be left alone.
We must work as a team.
This is essential
for this second challenge,
for an effective ethical
and reasoned approach
to serve and benefit the pupils' learning.
There is also a third challenge
to be faced:
the challenge of novelty.
Since AI and data in education,
including in relation to
the traditional digital technology
that teachers can use,
introduce a complex and evolving systemic nature.
Actually,
the data that we propose as input
for an analysis of what is done
on the learning traces,
in particular,
if we take the case of adaptive learning
for example.
This means being able to consider the help
that will be given to me,
but which is not the help
that I could have had
from a fixed input
for a fixed expected result.
In other words, including in the exercise,
in a succession of exercises,
I will probably have elements
that will give me
strong or weak signals
about what the student will learn.
This means that
in my professional practice,
in my professional development,
I also have to get used to making good use
of the analyses that AI can provide
in data processing and numerous data,
sometimes over longer periods
than I can do it myself,
so that I can calmly approach things
that I had not necessarily planned
and consequently also adapt myself.
The professional culture of the teacher
is also at stake here,
but as in society as a whole,
with increased use of AI techniques
associated with
various digital tools and services.
In summary,
we can say that if the challenges
are mainly pedagogical and didactic,
especially
in the teacher-pupil relationship,
they are also a little broader
since they re-examine,
as always
with the use of digital technology,
and provide an opportunity
to rethink what we learn,
why we learn it and how we learn it.
To be able to test,
experiment and open up new possibilities,
thanks to a technique that enables
large amounts of data to be used over time
which are,
even when you are an excellent teacher,
very useful when you use them as an aid
and take full responsibility
for what you do.
That means that the human relationship
is also essential here.
Of course, it is the teacher who decides,
and not the machine in the end.