We have just trained our first programme.
Well done.
As we saw,
there's actually nothing magical about it.
First, we told it what we would show it,
and then we showed it some example images.
This is the learning phase.
The programme being trained
is called a 'model'.
It can now predict
which category an image belongs to.
Its prediction
is still a statistical approximation,
hence the percentage.
According to its calculation,
there is a greater chance
that this image belongs
to this category than another.
But can it detect everything?
If we teach it to recognise cats,
could it identify lions or tigers?
Can our programme be wrong?