Impressive, but what is it for?
Impressive, right?
All right, we agree.
The program doesn't see our categories,
but it associates the label we've chosen
with the examples we show it.
This ability to identify things
can be very useful,
and AIs are becoming increasingly common
in our day-to-day lives.
It can automatically translate text,
communicate with voice assistants
or improve medical diagnoses.
Computer scientists are also using it
to try to build autonomous cars,
but many uses are still to be invented
for the world of tomorrow,
which will be more beautiful, fairer,
more sustainable and simpler.
Helping people with reduced autonomy,
for example,
by developing applications
that can describe their surroundings
by seeing us
or enabling paralysed people
to write text.
Making work easier and more interesting
by automating certain repetitive tasks.
Limiting global warming
by allowing more accurate predictions
of the future.
Now that we know what AI is,
what else can we do with it?
What solutions can we invent
for the future?
How can we use it
in our day-to-day lives to help us?