Tricking the machine.
As you have seen,
data plays a key role in AI learning.
We can easily mislead the machine.
If you want to train AI,
you need thousands of examples
and you need to know what they are.
Nowadays, we can easily find examples
with labels to answer our AI problems.
You can create your own dataset
or use ready-made ones,
but as you know by now,
you have to be careful with such datasets
because you can easily get biased data
if you don't ask the right questions
or if you don't sort them properly.
There are two types of bias,
processing or statistical bias,
those that have to do
with poor data preparation,
and societal or cognitive bias,
those that have to do with human bias,
gender issues for example.
At the end of the day,
AI is human and what we put into it,
with both good intentions and biases.