Sexist?
What if it was our data...
You may have noticed
that our model recognised
all people with long hair as women
and all those with short hair as men.
Without realising it,
we provided it with data that was sorted
according to criteria
other than those we had defined.
How we sorted the data was influenced
by our perception of the problem.
When this happens,
we say the data is biased.
AI algorithms have been around
for a long time,
but they didn't work so well
because we lacked labelled data.
Today,
data is available in large quantities.
That's why AI is so widespread.
However, we have to be careful
because this data can contain biases.