What if we play with the data
to trick the machine?
The program will make predictions
based on the categories
we have defined and the examples
we have shown to it.
Once trained, it is possible to trick it.
For example,
there are jewellery items
that can deceive facial recognition,
and signs with patterns
that can bypass
automatic surveillance videos.
However, as we have learned,
we can also trick the machine
with our data.
For example, we can train a program
to recognise beautiful and ugly people,
by showing only our face
as an example of beautiful people.
Generally speaking,
all the subjective categories,
such as cute, not cute,
stupid, intelligent,
depend on the person
who prepares the data.
We can also train a program
to recognise whether there are people
or not in the picture
by putting all our examples of faces
in the no people category.
This enables us to go incognito.
We will now hijack the data
to create a biased program.
How can we trick the machine
with our data?