So, are you a good
discriminating neural network?
Each time the generated image is considered
as real by the discriminator network,
the generative network reinforces
its parameters and progressively improves.
Some elements of the image
can particularly betray a generative AI:
the background of the image,
the teeth,
the asymmetry of the face or eyes,
unexpected blurred areas,
a hair a bit strange.
If you look carefully,
the images generated by GANs
are still recognizable,
but these bugs may well be corrected
in the years to come and it will be
increasingly difficult to distinguish them!
Want to try again?
It's up to you!